<!-- ArticleInstanceId : 4310221, Path: jbt/olf-9999/olf/preload/nxml/, Name : jbt.15-2601-001-jbt.15-2601-001.nxml -->
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d2 20140930//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
  article-type="research-article">
  <?OLF?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Biomol Tech</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Biomol Tech</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jbt</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">jbt</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">J Biomol Tech</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Biomolecular Techniques : JBT</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1524-0215</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1943-4731</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Association of Biomolecular Resource Facilities</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Bethesda, MD, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">JBT_2015-2601-001</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7171/jbt.15-2601-001</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Evaluation of Commercially Available RNA Amplification Kits for RNA
          Sequencing Using Very Low Input Amounts of Total RNA</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Shanker</surname>
            <given-names>Savita</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="afn1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Paulson</surname>
            <given-names>Ariel</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="afn1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Edenberg</surname>
            <given-names>Howard J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Peak</surname>
            <given-names>Allison</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Perera</surname>
            <given-names>Anoja</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Alekseyev</surname>
            <given-names>Yuriy O.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Beckloff</surname>
            <given-names>Nicholas</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">
            <sup>5</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bivens</surname>
            <given-names>Nathan J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">
            <sup>6</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Donnelly</surname>
            <given-names>Robert</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7">
            <sup>7</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gillaspy</surname>
            <given-names>Allison F.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff8">
            <sup>8</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Grove</surname>
            <given-names>Deborah</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff9">
            <sup>9</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gu</surname>
            <given-names>Weikuan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff10">
            <sup>10</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jafari</surname>
            <given-names>Nadereh</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff11">
            <sup>11</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kerley-Hamilton</surname>
            <given-names>Joanna S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff12">
            <sup>12</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lyons</surname>
            <given-names>Robert H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff13">
            <sup>13</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tepper</surname>
            <given-names>Clifford</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff14">
            <sup>14</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Nicolet</surname>
            <given-names>Charles M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff15">
            <sup>15</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff>
          <target id="aff1" target-type="aff">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </target>Genomic Division, Interdisciplinary Center for Biotechnology Research, University
          of Florida, Gainesville, Florida 32610, USA; <target id="aff2" target-type="aff">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </target>Stowers Institute for Medical Research, Kansas City, Missouri 64112, USA; <target
            id="aff3" target-type="aff">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </target>Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, Indiana University School of
          Medicine, Indianapolis, Indiana 46202-5122, USA; <target id="aff4" target-type="aff">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </target>Department of Pathology and Laboratory Medicine, Boston University School of
          Medicine, Boston, Massachusetts 02118, USA; <target id="aff5" target-type="aff">
            <sup>5</sup>
          </target>Research Technology Support Facility, Office of the Vice President for Research
          and Graduate Studies, Michigan State University, East Lansing, Michigan 48824, USA;
            <target id="aff6" target-type="aff">
            <sup>6</sup>
          </target>DNA Core Facility,Office of Research, University of Missouri, Columbia, Missouri
          65211, USA; <target id="aff7" target-type="aff">
            <sup>7</sup>
          </target>New Jersey Medical School&#x02013;Molecular Resource Facility, Rutgers Biomedical
          and Health Sciences, Rutgers University, Newark, New Jersey 08863, USA; <target id="aff8"
            target-type="aff">
            <sup>8</sup>
          </target>College of Medicine, Laboratory for Molecular Biology and Cytometry Research,
          Department of Microbiology and Immunology, The University of Oklahoma Health Sciences
          Center, Oklahoma City, Oklahoma 73104, USA; <target id="aff9" target-type="aff">
            <sup>9</sup>
          </target>Huck Institutes of the Life Sciences, The Pennsylvania State University,
          University Park, Pennsylvania 16802, USA; <target id="aff10" target-type="aff">
            <sup>10</sup>
          </target>Department of Orthopaedic Surgery and Biomedical Engineering, College of
          Medicine, University of Tennessee Health Sciences Center, Memphis, Tennessee 38163, USA;
            <target id="aff11" target-type="aff">
            <sup>11</sup>
          </target>Genomics Core Facility Center for Genetic Medicine, Feinberg School of Medicine,
          Northwestern University, Chicago, Illinois 60611, USA; <target id="aff12"
            target-type="aff">
            <sup>12</sup>
          </target>Norris Cotton Cancer Center, Geisel School of Medicine at Dartmouth College,
          Hanover, New Hampshire 03756, USA; <target id="aff13" target-type="aff">
            <sup>13</sup>
          </target>University of Michigan DNA Sequencing Core, Biomedical Research Core Facilities,
          University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, Michigan 48109, USA; <target id="aff14"
            target-type="aff">
            <sup>14</sup>
          </target>Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Medicine, University of
          California&#x02014;Davis, School of Medicine, Sacramento, California 95817, USA; and
            <target id="aff15" target-type="aff">
            <sup>15</sup>
          </target>Norris Comprehensive Cancer Center, Keck School of Medicine, University of
          Southern California, Los Angeles, California 90033, USA </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <fn id="afn1" fn-type="equal">
          <label>*</label>
          <p>These authors contributed equally to this work.</p>
        </fn>
        <corresp id="cor1">
          <sc>Address correspondence</sc> to: Charles Nicolet, 1450 Biggy Street, Los Angeles, CA
          90033, USA (Phone: 323-442-7988; FAX: 323-442-7880; E-mail:
            <email>cnicolet@usc.edu</email>). </corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>29</day>
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <elocation-id>jbt.15-2601-001</elocation-id>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#x000a9; Federation of American Societies for Experimental
          Biology</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Association of Biomolecular Resource Facilities</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="jbt.15-2601-001-jbt.15-2601-001.pdf"/>
      <abstract>
        <p>This article includes supplemental data. Please visit <italic>
            <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fasebj.org"
              >http://www.fasebj.org</ext-link>
          </italic> to obtain this information.Multiple recent publications on RNA sequencing
          (RNA-seq) have demonstrated the power of next-generation sequencing technologies in
          whole-transcriptome analysis. Vendor-specific protocols used for RNA library construction
          often require at least 100 ng total RNA. However, under certain conditions, much less RNA
          is available for library construction. In these cases, effective transcriptome profiling
          requires amplification of subnanogram amounts of RNA. Several commercial RNA amplification
          kits are available for amplification prior to library construction for next-generation
          sequencing, but these kits have not been comprehensively field evaluated for accuracy and
          performance of RNA-seq for picogram amounts of RNA. To address this, 4 types of
          amplification kits were tested with 3 different concentrations, from 5 ng to 50 pg, of a
          commercially available RNA. Kits were tested at multiple sites to assess reproducibility
          and ease of use. The human total reference RNA used was spiked with a control pool of RNA
          molecules in order to further evaluate quantitative recovery of input material. Additional
          control data sets were generated from libraries constructed following polyA selection or
          ribosomal depletion using established kits and protocols. cDNA was collected from the
          different sites, and libraries were synthesized at a single site using established
          protocols. Sequencing runs were carried out on the Illumina platform. Numerous metrics
          were compared among the kits and dilutions used. Overall, no single kit appeared to meet
          all the challenges of small input material. However, it is encouraging that excellent data
          can be recovered with even the 50 pg input total RNA. </p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>cDNA synthesis kits</kwd>
        <kwd>polyA</kwd>
        <kwd>ribodepletion</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <page-count count="15"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name> DJS Export </meta-name>
          <meta-value>v1</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s1">
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>For over a decade, hybridization-based approaches (microarrays) have been the method of
        choice for comprehensive assessment of RNA expression. The advent of next-generation
        sequencing (NGS) allowed a potentially more comprehensive way to measure expression
          level,<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">
          <sup>1</sup>
        </xref>
        <sup>&#x02013;</sup>
        <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">
          <sup>3</sup>
        </xref> identify alternative RNA processing,<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">
          <sup>4</sup>
        </xref>
        <sup>,</sup>
        <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">
          <sup>5</sup>
        </xref> and discover new genes<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">
          <sup>6</sup>
        </xref> by allowing RNA analysis through sequencing of cDNA at massively parallel scales.
        This procedure is denoted RNA sequencing (RNA-seq). </p>
      <p>RNA-seq has been widely used for whole-transcriptome analysis, yet often faces the
        limitation of requiring at least 100 ng total RNA for library construction. Sometimes, it is
        not possible to obtain that much RNA, for example, if one is working with single cells or
        small clinical samples. Methods for constructing RNA libraries from low starting amounts of
        RNA in a high-throughput and reproducible manner are thus required. For instance, Tang et
          al.<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">
          <sup>7</sup>
        </xref>
        <sup>,</sup>
        <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">
          <sup>8</sup>
        </xref> used a modified protocol that has been initially developed for single-cell
        microarray analysis to perform transcriptome analysis using individual mouse oocytes and
        early embryonic cells. To further address this need, several vendors have recently developed
        RNA amplification kits designed to use low starting input amounts. Results from one such kit
        (SMARTer; Clontech, Mountain View, CA, USA) performing RNA-seq from individual circulating
        tumor cells and single neurons have been reported.<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">
          <sup>9</sup>
        </xref>
        <sup>,</sup>
        <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">
          <sup>10</sup>
        </xref> More recently, in-house developed protocols have been used to examine gene
        expression from single cells in developing embryos.<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">
          <sup>11</sup>
        </xref> Vendors have also optimized or retooled RNA amplification kits that were initially
        developed for microarray analysis. Tariq et al.<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">
          <sup>12</sup>
        </xref> applied the Ovation RNA-Seq System (NuGEN Technologies Incorporated, San Carlos, CA,
        USA) to do whole-transcriptome RNA-seq analysis from minute amounts of total RNA isolated
        from mouse tissue. </p>
      <p>In response to the increased interest in working with small amounts of input material,
        numerous protocols have been developed, tested, and compared in different laboratories.<xref
          rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">
          <sup>11</sup>
        </xref>
        <sup>,</sup>
        <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">
          <sup>13</sup>
        </xref>
        <sup>&#x02013;</sup>
        <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">
          <sup>15</sup>
        </xref> One limitation of the comparison experiments is that they are all done in the same
        lab, sometimes the lab that developed a procedure, and it can be difficult to extrapolate
        those results to a broader group of researchers. </p>
      <p>This paper reports the results of a field evaluation of low-input RNA amplification kits
        carried out by the DNA Sequence Research Group (DSRG) of the Association of Biomolecular
        Resource Facilities (ABRF). One novel aspect of this study is that the work is done in many
        different core laboratories, allowing comparison of the output material across different
        generation sites.</p>
      <p>The ABRF DSRG compared RNA-seq results from standardized RNA samples using 4 different
        kits: Ovation RNA amplification kit, SMARTer amplification kit, TransPLEX-WTA2-SEQ kit
        (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA), and SuperAMP kit (Miltenyi Biotech, San Diego, CA,
        USA). To assess how the kits worked across different amounts of starting RNA, we amplified
        and sequenced 3 dilutions (5 ng, 500 pg, and 50 pg) of a standard commercial RNA (Clontech)
        spiked with External RNA Control Consortium (ERCC) control RNAs (Ambion, Life Technologies,
        Carlsbad, CA, USA). The reproducibility of these 4 kits was tested by performing
        amplification with each kit type at 3 core facilities, for a total of 12 participating
        sites. RNA and amplification kits were distributed by the DSRG to the participating core
        facilities to conduct amplification. Amplified cDNA samples were then collected by the DSRG
        for library construction at a single site (to reduce variability not associated with the
        amplification itself) with the Illumina TruSeq RNA kit (Illumina Incorporated, San Diego,
        CA, USA). Illumina TruSeq mRNA libraries were also prepared using 5 ng, 100 ng, and 1
          <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g total RNA spiked with ERCC control Mix 1 and 100 ng and 1
          <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g ribosomal-depleted RNA spiked with ERCC control Mix 1 as
        standards. All libraries were pooled and sequenced on the Illumina HiSeq 2000 platform. The
        data obtained from all samples were used to assess the effects of RNA abundance on the
        amplification kits under study.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2">
      <title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title>
      <sec id="s3">
        <title>Input Material</title>
        <p>The human universal reference total RNA [(part number) 636538; Clontech] spiked in with
          ERCC control mix (part number 4456740) was used in this study. The quality of the RNA (RNA
          integrity number 8.2) was determined on the Agilent 2100 Bioanalyzer (Agilent
          Technologies, Palo Alto, CA, USA) as per the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4">
        <title>Control &#x0201c;Standard&#x0201d; RNA-Seq Library Construction</title>
        <p>To construct libraries for unamplified control suitable for Illumina sequencing, the
          total RNA sample was processed using both the polyA-based TruSeq V2 as well as a
          ribo-depletion-based mRNA enrichment method (Epicentre, Madison, WI, USA).</p>
        <p>The polyA-based TruSeq V2 RNA sample preparation kit was used following the
          low-throughput modified protocol according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions.
          Because neither of the kits for the control data sets is configured to use the low
          starting amounts used for the other kits, input amounts of 5 ng, 100 ng, and 1
            <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g total RNA were tested. It should be noted that 5 ng is
          20-fold lower than the recommended minimum for the TruSeq kit.</p>
        <p>For the ribo-depletion method, 100 ng and 1 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g total RNA were
          used for ribosomal depletions using the Ribo-Zero Gold Kit for human, mouse, or rat (part
          number MRZG12324; Epicentre) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions.</p>
        <p>Both the polyA and rRNA-depleted RNAs were subjected to thermal fragmentation using the
          elute, prime, and fragment mix from the TruSeq RNA sample preparation kit. RNA fragments
          were then converted to double-stranded (ds) cDNA using reverse transcriptase and random
          primers provided in the TruSeq RNA library preparation kit. The end repair, dA-tailing,
          ligation of bar-coded adaptors (PN. 514104; Bioo Scientific, Austin, TX, USA) to cDNA
          fragments for Illumina sequencing and AMPure purification steps (Beckman Coulter Genomics,
          Brea, CA, USA) were done on the Tecan Freedom EVO Liquid Handling Robot (Tecan Group,
          M&#x000e4;nnedorf, Switzerland).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s5">
        <title>Generation of cDNA Using RNA Amplification Kits</title>
        <p>The same batch of RNA and ERCC control mix was shipped to 12 different laboratories on
          dry ice. For comparison studies between amplification kits, each participant was
          instructed to combine 1 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>l total RNA (1
            <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g/<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>l) with 2
            <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>l of 1:100 dilution of ERCC spike-in mix 1 and 7
            <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>l water. Serial dilutions (5 ng, 500 pg, and 50 pg) of the
          initial RNA cocktail (100 ng/<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>l) were used as substrates for
          amplification reactions using the manufacturer&#x02019;s recommended protocols.</p>
        <p>There were 4 different RNA amplification kits used in this study: SMARTer Ultra Low input
          RNA (part number 634935); SuperAmp (R&#x00026;D Systems, Minneapolis, MN, USA); Ovation
          RNA-Seq System V2 (part number 7102; NuGEN Technologies Incorporated); and SeqPlex RNA
          (Sigma-Aldrich; R&#x00026;D Systems). Kits were generously provided by the suppliers.</p>
        <sec id="s6">
          <title>SMARTer cDNA Synthesis</title>
          <p>For cDNA synthesis using the SMARTer Ultra Low RNA-Seq System, RNA samples were primed
            with modified Oligo-dT primer (SMART CDS primer II A
            5&#x02032;-AAGCAGTGGTATCAACGCAGAGTACT(30) N-1N-3&#x02032;, where N = A, C, G, or T, and
            N-1 = A, G, or C), and first-strand synthesis was carried out using SMARTScribe
            (Clontech) reverse transcriptase (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
              xlink:href="http://JBT.fasebj.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.7171/jbt.15-2601-001/-/DC1"
              >Supplemental Fig. 1</ext-link>). Once the reverse-transcriptase reaction reaches the
            5&#x02032; end of an RNA molecule, the terminal transferase activity of Moloney murine
            leukemia virus adds a few nontemplated bases to the 3&#x02032; end of cDNA. The SMARTer
            II A Oligonucleotide (5&#x02032;-AAGCAGTGGTATCAACGCAGAGTACXXXXX-3&#x02032;, where X =
            undisclosed bases) then base pairs with the nontemplate nucleotide stretch, creating an
            extended template. The SMARTScribe then switches template and continues transcribing to
            the end of oligonucleotide. The resulting full-length, single-stranded (ss) cDNA
            contains the complete 5&#x02032; end of the mRNA, as well as anchor sequences that are
            complementary to the SMARTer Oligonucleotide for second-strand synthesis. The ds cDNA
            was purified using Agencourt AMPure beads (Beckman Coulter Genomics). The purified cDNA
            was then amplified by long-distance PCR using the Advantage 2 PCR Kit (part number
            639206; Clontech) and the included PCR primer
            (5&#x02032;-AAGCAGTGGTATCAACGCAGAGT-3&#x02032;) for 12 PCR cycles (5 ng), 14 PCR cycles
            (500 pg), and 17 cycles (50 pg) in 50 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>l reaction according to
            the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s7">
          <title>SuperAMP cDNA Synthesis</title>
          <p>RNA samples were combined with 5 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>l supermagnetic MACS
            MicroBeads (Miltenyi Biotec) for mRNA isolation (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
              xlink:href="http://JBT.fasebj.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.7171/jbt.15-2601-001/-/DC1"
              >Supplemental Fig. 2</ext-link>). The bead-RNA mixture was applied to a column and
            rinsed to remove rRNA and other contaminants. First-strand cDNA mix was added, then
            in-column cDNA synthesis was carried out at 42&#x000b0;C for 45 min. After rinsing, the
            3&#x02032; tailing mix was applied on top of the column matrix and incubated at
            37&#x000b0;C for 1 h for 3&#x02032; tailing of ss cDNA. After washing steps, the column
            was removed from the thermoMACS separator (Miltenyi Biotec) and placed into a 0.2 ml PCR
            tube. Resuspended PCR mix (New England Biolabs, Ipswich, MA, USA) was applied to elute
            material from the magnetic beads. A total of 2 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>l New England
            Biolabs Phusion High-Fidelity DNA polymerase was added to the eluate and amplified ss
            cDNA by running SuperAMP PCR for 40 cycles. The ds cDNA was then purified using the High
            Pure PCR Product Purification Kit (Roche, Basel, Switzerland) following the
            manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. This Miltenyi Biotec product was a prerelease item
            provided by Miltenyi Biotec for the purposes of this project. Following discussions
            between Miltenyi Biotec scientists and participating researchers, they have further
            improved their protocol by optimizing the bead composition and reducing the final number
            of PCR cycles. These changes have not been evaluated in this study.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s8">
          <title>Ovation cDNA Synthesis</title>
          <p>For cDNA synthesis with the Ovation RNA-Seq kit, RNA samples were reverse transcribed
            by using a combination of random hexamers and poly-T RNA/DNA chimeric primer mix
              (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
              xlink:href="http://JBT.fasebj.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.7171/jbt.15-2601-001/-/DC1"
              >Supplemental Fig. 3</ext-link>). The ds cDNA with a unique DNA/RNA heteroduplex at
            one end was then generated by fragmentation of the mRNA using RNA-dependent DNA
            polymerase. The resulting cDNA was then purified using RNAClean XP purification beads
            (Beckman Coulter, Brea, CA, USA). The purified cDNA was then subjected to linear
            amplification by the so-called single primer isothermal amplification (SPIA) process. In
            this protocol, DNA/RNA chimeric SPIA primer binding, DNA replication, strand
            displacement, and RNA cleavage are repeated for multiple rounds, resulting in
            accumulation of SPIA cDNA. Random hexamer priming was then used to convert ss-SPIA cDNA
            to ds cDNA.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s9">
          <title>SeqPlex cDNA Synthesis</title>
          <p>With the SeqPlex RNA amplification kit, the RNA samples were reverse transcribed with
            random primers having semidegenerate 3&#x02032; ends and defined universal 5&#x02032;
            ends (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
              xlink:href="http://JBT.fasebj.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.7171/jbt.15-2601-001/-/DC1"
              >Supplemental Fig. 4</ext-link>). The displaced single strands generated during the
            process serve as a template for primer annealing and second-strand cDNA synthesis. The
            resultant ds cDNA flanked by a single universal primer was amplified by 17&#x02013;19
            cycles of PCR. The cDNA was then purified using the GenElute PCR Clean-Up Kit (catalog
            number NA1020; Sigma-Aldrich) or AMPure beads (part number A63881; Beckman Coulter
            Genomics). Finally, the primer at both ends was removed using primer removal enzyme
            followed by purification using the GenElute PCR Clean-Up Kit or AMPure beads
            (Agencourt).</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s10">
        <title>Construction of Libraries from Amplified cDNA</title>
        <p>The yield of all the amplified products was measured using a Qubit (Invitrogen, Carlsbad,
          CA, USA). The fragment size of the purified ds cDNA was assessed on the Agilent 2100
          Bioanalyzer. Details of the amount of cDNA recovered, fragment sizes of amplified cDNA for
          each dilution, and difficulty level of the kits are included in <ext-link
            ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://JBT.fasebj.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.7171/jbt.15-2601-001/-/DC1"
            >Supplemental Table 1</ext-link>.</p>
        <p>All kits except the Sigma-Aldrich SeqPlex RNA amplification kit generated cDNA that
          required fragmentation prior to library generation. Fragmentation was carried out with a
          Covaris S220 AFA Ultrasonicator (Woburn, MA, USA) using the recommended conditions for
          generating 200&#x02013;500 bp fragments. When possible, 500 ng cDNA was used for
          subsequent manipulations, though frequently the entire sample was used (<ext-link
            ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://JBT.fasebj.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.7171/jbt.15-2601-001/-/DC1"
            >Supplemental Table 1</ext-link>). All the libraries were constructed on the Tecan
          Freedom EVO300 Liquid Handling Robot using the TruSeq DNA Sample Preparation kit reagents
          at a single site (Stowers Institute, Kansas City, MO, USA). All adapter ligation mixes
          were amplified for 12 cycles. Finished libraries were purified from free adaptor product
          using AMPure beads (Agencourt). The resulting purified libraries were quantitated using a
          Qubit, and the size range of the products was confirmed by Caliper&#x02019;s LabChip GX
            (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://JBT.fasebj.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.7171/jbt.15-2601-001/-/DC1"
            >Supplemental Table 2</ext-link>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s11">
        <title>Sequencing</title>
        <p>The indexed 35 cDNA libraries (30 from amplified and 5 from nonamplified cDNA) were
          combined in equimolar ratios into 1 pool and loaded into 7 lanes of the Illumina HiSeq
          2000 for a 50-cycle sequencing run, with the Illumina PhiX sample used as control. A new
          pool was created for underrepresented libraries (based on the data generated using the
          first pool) and subjected to sequencing on another 5 lanes of HiSeq 2000. Image analysis
          and base calling were performed using Illumina pipeline version 1.5.15.1. Average number
          of total reads is shown in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://JBT.fasebj.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.7171/jbt.15-2601-001/-/DC1"
            >Supplemental Table 3</ext-link>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s12">
        <title>Alignments</title>
        <p>Reads were aligned with TopHat 2.0.6 (Bowtie 2.0.2): bt2-very-sensitive setting, Ensembl
          66 Gene Transfer Format (GTF), to University of California, Santa Cruz (UCSC) hg19. The
          Ensembl GTF was modified to reflect UCSC chromosome names. Read hits to genomic features
          were quantitated using intersectBed.</p>
        <p>There were 2 additional alignment versions made: 1 without multireads (Unique), and
          another with no multireads and with only 1 read per unique start position in the genome
          (Unique-Rmdup), for purposes of comparison. Library complexity was examined using read
          uniqueness, as (N unique reads) / (N total reads), for each sample.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s13">
        <title>ERCC Controls</title>
        <p>Unaligned reads were aligned to ERCC92 sequences (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://tools.invitrogen.com/downloads/ERCC92.fa"
            >http://tools.invitrogen.com/downloads/ERCC92.fa</ext-link>) with Bowtie 2.0.2: very
          fast setting and quantitated with samtools idxstats. Observed relative spike
          concentrations were correlated to expected (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://tools.invitrogen.com/content/sfs/manuals/cms_095046.txt"
            >http://tools.invitrogen.com/content/sfs/manuals/cms_095046.txt</ext-link>) and plotted.
          Sample similarities were measured by Pearson correlation of all ERCC values.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s14">
        <title>Reads per Kilobase of Exon per Million Reads</title>
        <p>Exon- and junction-aligning reads were converted into reads per kilobase of exon per
          million reads (RPKMs) per sample, where M is the total number of exon- and
          junction-aligned reads for all genes per sample. Sample similarities were measured by
          Pearson correlation of all gene RPKMs.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s15">
        <title>Gene Detection</title>
        <p>All read sets were randomly down sampled to 10 million reads to avoid biases in gene
          detection due to differential number of recovered reads. Stochasticity in detections was
          addressed in 2 ways: 1) down sampling was repeated 5 times; and 2) gene detectability was
          calculated using 1, 2, or 5 reads. Detectability of each Ensembl gene biotype was
          evaluated for all methods.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s16">
        <title>Gene Coverage</title>
        <p>For each gene and sample, base-by-base read depth values were extracted from the
          whole-genome BedGraph file. Intronic positions were removed, coverage vectors for
          minus-strand genes were reversed, and remaining values divided into 100 bins and averaged
          to produce a uniform 100-column matrix of gene coverage&#x02019;s for each sample. Genes
          shorter than 100 bp were dropped. Global coverage bias per sample was graphed by
          converting rows of the matrix to Z scores and plotting the column sums. Gene-wise trends
          in coverage bias and variability were investigated by taking the coefficient of variance
          of the original coverage vector per gene and also by taking the ratio of the first-quarter
          mean depth (5&#x02032; coverage) to fourth-quarter mean depth (3&#x02032; coverage) on the
          gene body.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results" id="s17">
      <title>RESULTS</title>
      <sec id="s18">
        <title>Library Generation</title>
        <p>One of the primary goals in many ABRF Research Group studies is the assessment of
          site-to-site variability in experimental manipulations. For the current low-input study,
          12 sites participated in the comparison of 4 kits, with 3 sites per kit. There were 2
          sites unable to generate material resulting in sequenceable libraries. Because reagents
          for these studies are donated by the manufacturers, it is not always possible to repeat
          compromised experiments. Thus, data series for 2 sites are unavailable.</p>
        <p>Control universal human reference RNA, representing a pool of total RNA from different
          human tissues, was distributed to the sites. As described in MATERIALS AND METHODS, all
          kit manufacturers&#x02019; protocols were faithfully followed to generate cDNA. The
          resulting output cDNA was quantified by Qubit and further characterized by bioanalyzer.
          The different kits produced patterns and sizes of cDNAs stereotypical for each kit but
          distinct from each other. Representative trace files are shown in <ext-link
            ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://JBT.fasebj.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.7171/jbt.15-2601-001/-/DC1"
            >Supplemental Table 1</ext-link>. The cDNAs from all sites were sent to The Stowers
          Institute for library production and sequencing on the Illumina HiSeq platform; details of
          the syntheses are provided in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://JBT.fasebj.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.7171/jbt.15-2601-001/-/DC1"
            >Supplemental Table 1</ext-link>. The control libraries were also produced at Stowers
          Institute. Because all libraries were synthesized simultaneously, using automation
          throughout, it is expected that variances at the construction step will be as controlled
          for as possible. Libraries were evaluated by Bioanalyzer analysis prior to sequencing
            (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://JBT.fasebj.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.7171/jbt.15-2601-001/-/DC1"
            >Supplemental Table 2</ext-link>).</p>
        <p>Despite similarities in the bioanalyzer appearance of the libraries, they exhibited
          different behaviors on the sequencer. The Clontech samples showed the strong presence of a
          particular sequence derived from the SMART adapters used during amplification. This is a
          known contaminant with this system (Clontech, personal communication). The Miltenyi Biotec
          samples demonstrated more rapid decline in base quality over the course of the run, though
          the cause is not known. Because these are from samples prepared at different sites, it
          seems probable that they represent common outcomes from these kits (Fastqc results not
          shown).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s19">
        <title>Analysis</title>
        <p>Various sequencing metric and data comparisons were carried out to assess the output of
          the different kits. In some cases, the analyses utilized the entire data set generated
          from a particular kit, whereas other analyses were normalized to the same number of reads
          in an attempt to emphasize the validity of the comparisons (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://JBT.fasebj.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.7171/jbt.15-2601-001/-/DC1"
            >Supplemental Table 3</ext-link>). Control data sets were generated from libraries using
          established commercial reagents and suggested protocols for construction. Although
          providing an essential analytic comparison, data sets from these TruSeq polyA-based and
          Ribo-Zero ribo-depleted libraries were generated with much more starting material, i.e.,
          under less-challenging conditions. Therefore, these libraries would be expected to perform
          better. Another important caveat is that the lowest RNA concentration of 50 pg was out of
          specifications for the Sigma-Aldrich and NuGEN Technologies Incorporated kits, whereas the
          lowest amount of RNA used in the TruSeq V2 kit, 5 ng, was also out of the
          manufacturer-recommended range of starting material.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s20">
        <title>Read Mapping and Library Complexity</title>
        <p>Initial analyses focused on the basic parameters of mapped reads and read compositions.
          All the reads from each kit and concentration were used for these calculations. <xref
            ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref> shows the percent distributions of reads into
          those that aligned, reads that aligned and uniquely mapped, and uniquely mapping reads
          from which duplicate reads have been removed (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://JBT.fasebj.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.7171/jbt.15-2601-001/-/DC1"
            >Supplemental Table 3</ext-link> shows the data from which these figures were derived).
          Several trends are observable. One is that the percent distribution of aligned reads for a
          given kit is not greatly affected by input concentrations. Another observation is that
          site-to-site variability using different kits appears small. Finally, whereas all methods
          produced predominantly uniquely mapping reads, the percentage of duplicate reads (those
          beginning with the same chromosomal coordinates) varied substantially between kits and
          across the concentration ranges detected, with the lowest input amounts showing the
          largest percentage of putative PCR duplicates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>
          and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://JBT.fasebj.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.7171/jbt.15-2601-001/-/DC1"
            >Supplemental Table 3</ext-link>). The results revealed that the highest percentage of
          unique reads was generated by Clontech, which showed unique read values very close to
          those generated by the control libraries. The Miltenyi Biotec and Sigma-Aldrich kits
          produced the lowest percentage of unique sequences.</p>
        <fig id="F1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Read composition comparison. The percentage of all recovered reads falling into
              particular categories is shown: red indicates all aligning reads, yellow represents
              all aligning reads mapping to a unique genomic location, and blue shows the uniquely
              mapping reads with putative PCR duplicates (i.e., reads starting at the same
              coordinate) removed. The numbers represent the different sites providing the starting
              cDNA from the indicated kits; RNA concentrations from high to low are represented by
              the blue triangles. RZ, Ribo-Zero; TS, TruSeq.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jbt.15-2601-001-jbt.15-2601-001_f1"/>
        </fig>
        <p>The distribution of reads across several broad biologic categories, i.e., read
          composition, is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>. These comparisons
          are shown with duplicate reads included (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>) and
          removed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>). The most noticeable and important
          trend here is that polyA selection-based methods (Clontech, Miltenyi Biotec, and
          &#x0201c;TS&#x0201d; for Illumina TruSeq kit) show a substantially higher proportion of
          exonic reads than the ribo-depletion-based methods (NuGEN Technologies Incorporated,
          Sigma-Aldrich, and &#x0201c;RZ&#x0201d; for Ribo-Zero). This difference can be up to
          4-fold in certain pairwise comparisons, an important factor when deciding the number of
          reads required to match a specific experimental goal. The loss of reads in the exonic
          compartment was primarily due to the increased number of rRNA reads (&#x0223c;35% for
          NuGEN Technologies Incorporated and &#x0223c;29% for Sigma-Aldrich) and intronic reads
          (representing unprocessed or partially processed transcripts). Although NuGEN Technologies
          Incorporated and Sigma-Aldrich had many more rRNA reads than Ribo-Zero-depleted material,
          the intronic fraction was higher in the latter. Removal of putative PCR duplicates (i.e.,
          reads starting at the same nucleotide) had varying effects on read representation. For
          NuGEN Technologies Incorporated and Sigma-Aldrich, whereas the proportion of exonic reads
          increased overall, the proportion of intronic reads increased more. For Miltenyi Biotec,
          Clontech, and both control libraries, the exonic read proportion actually decreased.</p>
        <fig id="F2" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <p>(A) Comparison of RNA category percentages. The percent composition of several broad
              categories of RNAs is displayed; 100% represents the total number of uniquely aligning
              reads for each sample set. Blue indicates exonic reads, red shows intronic, yellow
              represents ribosomal, purple indicates intergenic, aqua shows novel splice junctions,
              and green indicates known splice junctions. The kits used and participating sites are
              indicated, with RNA input amounts from highest to lowest represented by blue
              triangles. (B) Comparison of RNA category percentages. Designations shown are the same
              as those in (A), except the putative PCR duplicates have been removed from these data
              sets prior to percent category calculations.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jbt.15-2601-001-jbt.15-2601-001_f2"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s21">
        <title>Gene Abundance and Biotype Comparisons</title>
        <p>The sensitivity of gene detection was assessed for each input amount of RNA and kit. This
          comparison, based on a detection threshold of 2 reads, is shown in <xref ref-type="fig"
            rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>. The genes used are the GRCh37 Ensembl version 66 compilations of
          53,598 genes. To normalize detection for the variable read numbers recovered, 5 random
          samplings of 10 million reads each were carried out per library (the lowest read count for
          any library was 13.3 million). Detected genes are broken down into coding, noncoding, and
          pseudogenes. The composition of detected gene biotypes showed variability across protocols
          and dilutions. However, the number of genes detected reduced with lower amounts of input
          RNA. This trend was evident for all the low-input protocols tested and at most of the
          sites. The unamplified control, tested using 3 different amounts of input RNA (5 ng, 100
          ng, and 1 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g), was more robust. The results revealed that the 5
          ng Clontech and NuGEN Technologies Incorporated samples performed nearly as well as the
          control data sets, with Sigma-Aldrich very close. The Miltenyi Biotec protocol yielded the
          fewest number of detected genes, which may be a consequence of the large number of
          amplification cycles used in this protocol (see DISCUSSION).</p>
        <fig id="F3" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <p>(A) Detection sensitivity. The number of genes represented by 2 alignment hits is
              shown for the different construction kits and protocols; coding genes are shown in
              blue, ncRNAs in green, and pseudogenes in red. RNA concentrations going from high to
              low are represented by blue triangles, and the site numbers are indicated. The queried
              set is the Ensembl version 66 compilation of 53,599 genes. (B) Sensitivity of gene
              detection by gene type. The different biotypes are indicated on the left-hand side.
              For each library, detected gene percentages represent the mean from 5 different 10
              million read down samplings. Heatmap values are detected genes as percent detectable,
              detection requires &#x02265;2 reads, and &#x0201c;detectable&#x0201d; genes are those
              with &#x02265;2 reads in the 1 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g Ribo-Zero control. Kit
              types and dilutions are indicated as in the other figures.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jbt.15-2601-001-jbt.15-2601-001_f3"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Because both polyA and non-polyA-based kits were used, the proportion of gene biotypes
          recovered would be expected to differ substantially. To assess this, the detectability of
          different classes of noncoding and protein-coding RNAs was calculated and plotted on the
          heatmap in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3B</xref> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://JBT.fasebj.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.7171/jbt.15-2601-001/-/DC1"
            >Supplemental Table 4</ext-link>. For each sample and biotype, the number of genes
          detected by at least 2 reads in that sample is shown as a percentage of detectable genes
          in that biotype. The values for detectable genes in a particular biotype were determined
          experimentally: a gene was considered &#x0201c;detectable&#x0201d; if it had at least 2
          reads in the 1 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g Ribo-Zero control. Thus, by definition,
          Ribo-Zero detected the most genes in every biotype. The 50 pg libraries had substantial
          sensitivity loss in all biotypes; noncoding RNAs (ncRNAs) in particular showed up to 60%
          loss versus their 5 ng counterparts. Minimal detectability of small housekeeping ncRNAs
          like mi-, sn-, and snoRNAs, as well as their pseudogenes, is to be expected and may be due
          more to library size selection than to amplification bias. Performance of ribo-depleted
          libraries was more robust than polyA libraries across lowered input amounts: comparing
          detected genes at 5 ng and 50 pg for each kit, the ribo-depletion-based kits had average
          losses of 14 and 37% for protein-coding and ncRNAs, respectively, whereas the polyA-based
          kits had average losses of 30 and 52%.</p>
        <p>To determine if any potential biases in expression level are generated during
          amplification, RPKM values per gene were calculated for each kit. RPKMs showed the least
          variation among kits, sites, and dilutions. RPKMs were calculated using bedTools to count
          reads on exons. The distributions of 5 RPKM percentiles per library (0, 25, 50, 75, and
          100%) are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>. A consistent trend was
          that the maximum RPKMs are higher in the ribo-depleted libraries than polyA based; this is
          caused by the mitochondrial rRNAs and 1 somatic rRNA pseudogene.</p>
        <fig id="F4" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <p>RPKM measurements of detected reads. Gene abundance was quantified and divided into
              quantiles based on their relative levels. RNA concentrations going from high to low
              are represented by blue triangles, and the site numbers are indicated.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jbt.15-2601-001-jbt.15-2601-001_f4"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Because the goal of many RNA-seq experiments is to analyze differential gene expression
          among samples, it was of interest to quantify expression similarities between kits and
          dilutions. Expression profiles for all expressed genes were compared by Pearson
          correlation, using log2 (median RPKM), and displayed in a heatmap matrix shown in <xref
            ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5A</xref>. Specific sets of R values were extracted from
          the matrix and box plotted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5B</xref>. In accordance
          with earlier performance metrics, the 50 pg samples had low correlations with the control
          libraries, whereas 500 pg and 5 ng tended to behave similarly. Not surprisingly, at the
          higher input amounts, all kits had more similar expression profiles. Also, gene expression
          values in the ribo-depletion kits (NuGEN Technologies Incorporated and Sigma-Aldrich) were
          more similar to each other than were the polyA kits (Clontech and Miltenyi Biotec). The
          greater consistency in RPKMs for ribo-depleting kits parallels their increased gene
          detection. The NuGEN Technologies Incorporated kit appeared to have the least expression
          bias because it correlated best with both control libraries and also had highest intrakit
          R values. Furthermore, it appears that intersite variability is not substantially
          different from intrasite variability. For example, the correlations between the different
          input amounts within a site vary from 0.55 to &#x0223c;0.9, about the same range as the
          correlations within and between the concentrations among all sites.</p>
        <fig id="F5" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <p>(A) Gene expression comparisons. Pearson correlations among kits and across dilutions
              were graphed based on gene expression values. These values were derived from the
                Log<sub>2</sub>(Median Library RPKM) per gene. (B) Pairwise correlations of gene
              expression measurements. Values are displayed as box plots when sufficient data points
              are used, otherwise individual values are displayed.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jbt.15-2601-001-jbt.15-2601-001_f5"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s22">
        <title>Coverage Uniformity</title>
        <p>As discussed, the amplification kits and controls used here employ widely varying
          strategies for generating cDNA. It was therefore of interest to examine the uniformity of
          gene body coverage with the different kits. This is visualized in <xref ref-type="fig"
            rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>. For this figure, the coverage data from a particular kit were
          pooled for all RNA concentrations and across all sites. This was done because gene body
          coverage was not substantially affected by dilution or sites (data not shown). Analysis of
          read coverage across the exonic regions of genes demonstrated that all amplification kits
          showed 3&#x02032; biases in comparison to Ribo-Zero control sample. The Miltenyi Biotec
          and Smart kits&#x02019; polyA-based enrichment methods showed significant 3&#x02032; bias,
          followed by TruSeq and then NuGEN Technologies Incorporated, probably because NuGEN
          Technologies Incorporated uses both Oligo-dT and random primers during first-step cDNA
          synthesis. The Sigma-Aldrich kit displayed more even coverage after a pronounced but short
          3&#x02032; bias. Variation in 3&#x02032; bias per input concentration was negligible
          except for Miltenyi Biotec, which moderately increased in bias with increasing input. Our
          results also show a slight 5&#x02032; bias in Ribo-Zero samples.</p>
        <fig id="F6" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Gene body coverage. The mean coverage from all reporting genes and all samples from
              the different kits is displayed (i.e., all input concentrations and site data were
              pooled for a given kit). The figure shows the Z score across each bin, going from
              5&#x02032; to 3&#x02032; left to right. Exonic reads within detected genes were used
              for the calculations.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jbt.15-2601-001-jbt.15-2601-001_f6"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s23">
        <title>ERCC Controls</title>
        <p>The universal human reference RNA sample distributed to each site was spiked with an ERCC
          control prior to dilution. ERCC controls are synthetic polyadenylated transcript pools
          with each transcript present at known concentration. Comparison of these known
          concentrations with the values recovered in the experiment can provide a quantitative
          measure of sequence loss or bias during library preparation. ERCC analyses are shown in
            <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">
            <bold>Fig. 7</bold>
          </xref>, the Pearson correlation of ERCC RPKMs between samples displayed as a heatmap
          matrix is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7A</xref>, and Pearson correlations
          of observed versus expected concentrations are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig.
            7B</xref>. Despite the apparent spread in values in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig.
            7A</xref>, the lowest correlations measured (excluding Miltenyi Biotec) were
          &#x0003e;0.76. These results indicate that ERCC recovery was broadly consistent across
          treatments and concentrations. Similar to the other metrics displayed, intersite
          variability was low, and again the lowest dilution, 50 pg, was apparent through
          compromised performance. However, the degree of falloff seemed to be kit dependent, with
          the Clontech protocol showing the most consistent results across the dilution series.
            <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7B</xref> shows the log linearity of ERCC RPKMs
          because spike-in transcript concentrations have a logarithmic distribution. If the
          recovered concentrations of spike-ins equaled the expected concentrations, this value
          would be 1.0. Particularly at the 2 higher concentrations, all kits and sites performed
          similarly and were able to approach the expected level of expression. The Clontech kit did
          the best job of approaching the theoretic perfect value. </p>
        <fig id="F7" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Figure 7</label>
          <caption>
            <p>(A) ERCC standards expression. Pearson correlations among kits and across dilutions
              were graphed based on the recovered RPKM values of ERCC standards. Blue triangles
              indicate dilution series. (B) Log linearity of ERCC RPKM values. Box plots indicate
              expression levels relative to the known concentrations of the original standards
              present. A value of 1.0 indicates equivalence between the published standard values
              and the recovered values.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jbt.15-2601-001-jbt.15-2601-001_f7"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="s24">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>The ability to elucidate the transcriptome from a single or small number of cells will
        provide a high-resolution examination of basic processes like differentiation,
        carcinogenesis, and circulating cell physiology. A number of kits are currently available to
        assist this effort. These kits differ in their basic approaches, generally splitting into
        polyA-based versus ribo-depleted protocols. Suggested input concentrations can also vary.
        Two of the kits tested, NuGEN Technologies Incorporated and Sigma-Aldrich, were challenged
        with starting material amounts below the manufacturer&#x02019;s recommendations.</p>
      <p>It was of interest to see how the read composition and biotype distribution varied from kit
        to kit. These comparisons were made between kits but also between the low-input kits and
        data sets generated from libraries made using commonly utilized higher-input kits. The chief
        findings here are that the kits showed substantial differences in both the complexity of the
        libraries generated, as indicated by the percentage of duplicate reads (<xref ref-type="fig"
          rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>), and the distribution of recovered reads in different transcript
        compartments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). These latter differences in
        compartmentalization were to be expected because ribo-depletion-based kits (here,
        Sigma-Aldrich and NuGEN Technologies Incorporated) are known to generate substantially more
        reads in intronic regions and more rRNA reads. The proportion of rRNA reads, at least for
        the NuGEN Technologies Incorporated kit, was higher than expected based on a previously
        published study<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">
          <sup>12</sup>
        </xref> and manufacturer&#x02019;s reports (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
          xlink:href="http://www.nugeninc.com/nugen/index.cfm/products/cs/ngs/rna-seq-v2"
          >http://www.nugeninc.com/nugen/index.cfm/products/cs/ngs/rna-seq-v2</ext-link>/), but the
        fact that the values reported here were generated across all dilutions at different sites
        suggests that technical issues within the testing laboratories were not involved. The
        proportion of exonic reads was highest using the Miltenyi Biotec kit, but this metric alone
        is misleading because these libraries are among the least complex. Both this and the
        Sigma-Aldrich kits generated many more PCR duplicates than the other kits. The 50 pg
        libraries, whereas in general are less complex for all kits, controls, and sites, were
        particularly compromised for Miltenyi Biotec and Sigma-Aldrich, both probably being the
        prereleased kits (Miltenyi Biotec has since modified its protocol to include fewer PCR
        cycles, which is expected to improve this). A recent publication<xref rid="B13"
          ref-type="bibr">
          <sup>13</sup>
        </xref> covering some of the library preparation conditions tested here showed similar
        overall patterns. </p>
      <p>An important consideration with constructing libraries using low amounts of input material
        is the sensitivity of gene detection. This was assessed by examining the read occurrence of
        the known set of GRCh37 genes in the sample-specific data sets. <xref ref-type="fig"
          rid="F3">Figure 3A</xref> shows detection sensitivity for 3 broad classes of genes:
        protein coding, pseudogenes, and ncRNAs. Interestingly, there were not substantial
        differences between the polyA-based and ribo-depletion kits for this particular analysis.
        For the test kit samples, the least sensitive libraries were those constructed with the
        lowest amount of material. A more detailed breakdown of the biotypes, shown in <xref
          ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3B</xref>, indicates more subtle distinctions among the
        tested conditions. The heatmap indicates that the Ribo-Zero versus TruSeq controls in
        particular show noticeable differences for ncRNA biotype detection. However, overall, there
        are surprisingly minor differences between the kits with regard to the percentages of gene
        types detected. The main effect observed is that increasing dilution leads to decreased
        sensitivity at all the amounts tested. This behavior is not unexpected, but the difference
        between 5 ng and 500 pg seems a little more substantial than for many other metrics
        tested.</p>
      <p>A frequently desired goal of RNA-seq experiments is the assessment of differential gene
        expression. Comparison of recovered expression values should indicate the suitability of the
        different kits and dilutions for these experiments. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure
          4</xref> shows that for the detected reads, the RPKM values did not show substantial
        variability. The &#x0201c;Min&#x0201d; values, representing genes with the lowest RPKMs, had
        more spread, yet the median values were similar across all conditions and close to control
        values. This suggests that whereas all the kits might not identify the same spectrum of
        genes, expression values for the detected genes are accurate. Gene expression comparisons
        assessed by Pearson correlations further suggest the suitability of the different kits for
        quantitative comparisons, at least under certain conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5"
          >Fig. 5A</xref>). The 50 pg sample again showed the greatest divergence between kits and
        between the other dilutions with the same kit. Comparison of the correlations (<xref
          ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5B</xref>) reveals additional interesting data.
        Ribo-depletion approaches appear to have higher correlations and less spread than polyA
        protocols. The NuGEN Technologies Incorporated kit was better correlated to the controls.
        Somewhat surprisingly, given Clontech&#x02019;s excellence in other metrics, this kit showed
        less correlation with the controls than NuGEN Technologies Incorporated or Sigma-Aldrich.
        Correlations within kits also showed that NuGEN Technologies Incorporated and Sigma-Aldrich
        were tied for lowest variability. These results suggest that despite yielding a lower
        proportion of exonic reads, ribo-depletion approaches provide equivalent or superior
        quantitative expression data compared to the tested polyA approaches. In general, it would
        appear that cross kit, method, and dilution correlations outweigh intersite variability.
        This is an important component assessed in ABRF studies, but not in others in which multiple
        kits are tested in the same laboratory. The main source of variability did seem to be the
        success with which the kits were utilized&#x02014;2 of the sites with 2 different kits
        (Miltenyi Biotec and NuGEN Technologies Incorporated) were unable to generate cDNA suitable
        for subsequent library generation.</p>
      <p>Analysis of the expression level of the ERCC RNA standards is shown in <xref ref-type="fig"
          rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>. Pearson correlations displayed by heatmap in <xref ref-type="fig"
          rid="F7">Fig. 7A</xref> show the outcome observed in most other metric assessments, namely
        that the 50 pg samples behave notably poorer than the others in most pairwise combinations,
        whereas the 500 pg and 5 ng samples closely resemble each other. Nevertheless, all kits
        performed reasonably well, with Pearson correlation values rarely going below 0.8. The
        log-linearity plots in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7B</xref> emphasize this
        conclusion because all kits performed about as well as the controls (except for the 50 pg
        samples). Clontech actually exceeded the control values and came closest to recapitulating
        the actual amounts of the added ERCC standards.</p>
      <p>The main conclusions that emerge are that expression analyses using small input amounts of
        RNA, whereas challenging, are relatively consistent across laboratories and that several
        available kits work reasonably well. Both polyA and ribo-depleted protocols can do a good
        job recapitulating the transcriptome across a wide range of input concentrations. The middle
        input concentration of 500 pg behaved nearly identically to 5 ng in this and many other
        important sequencing metrics. At the lowest tested level of 50 pg input RNA, supposedly
        corresponding to 5 cells, nearly every sequencing quality metric was clearly compromised
        (though as noted for the Sigma-Aldrich and NuGEN Technologies Incorporated kits, this amount
        was outside recommendations). A reasonable assumption is that 5-fold lower input amounts
        (i.e., single cell) would lead to even more variability and compromised performance, at
        least with the kits tested here. Other studies, notably those using actual single cells and
        not diluted control RNAs, have borne this out.<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">
          <sup>10</sup>
        </xref> This study helps push down the lower input limit for standardized library
        performance. </p>
      <p>Another interesting finding is that kit protocols are often robust enough to perform well
        outside of the manufacturer&#x02019;s recommendations. With proper controls in place, such
        as ERCC spike-ins, a good strategy for labs would be to expand the usable parameters for the
        kits of choice. In general, the specific needs of the user and characteristics of the
        starting material will often dictate the choice of kits.</p>
      <p>An additional conclusion emerging from this study, though it was not directly addressed, is
        that determining how many reads are needed for an experiment is a complicated question. As
        is clear in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, exonic read proportions can vary
        widely depending on the kit and protocol used. Whether or not duplicate removal is required
        for a given analysis will also substantially influence the number of initial reads required.
        At these very small amounts, library complexity and sampling issues become important and
        need to be considered.</p>
      <p>Low-input RNA-seq analysis using different amplification kits has demonstrated some
        promising performance, but further development toward single-cell analysis is needed before
        it can be used as a routine application for basic and clinical research.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
      <title>Supplementary Material</title>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data">
        <label>Supplemental Figures</label>
        <media xlink:href="jbt.15-2601-001-jbt.15-2601-001-s01.docx">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data">
        <label>Supplemental Tables</label>
        <media xlink:href="jbt.15-2601-001-jbt.15-2601-001-s02.xlsx">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>The authors thank Clontech, Sigma-Aldrich, Miltenyi Biotech, and NuGEN Technologies
        Incorporated for providing reagents, kits, and technical support for the study. The authors
        thank Illumina for providing library preparation kits and sequencing reagents. The authors
        also thank the ABRF Executive Board for providing support for this study. Authors declare no
        competing financial interests.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Gerstein</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Snyder</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>RNA-Seq: a revolutionary tool for transcriptomics.</article-title>
          <source>Nat Rev Genet</source>
          <year>2009</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>57</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>63</lpage>. <pub-id
            pub-id-type="pmid">19015660</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mortazavi</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Williams</surname>
              <given-names>BA</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>McCue</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Schaeffer</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Wold</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mapping and quantifying mammalian transcriptomes by
            RNA-Seq.</article-title>
          <source>Nat Methods</source>
          <year>2008</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>621</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>628</lpage>.
            <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18516045</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ozsolak</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Milos</surname>
              <given-names>PM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>RNA sequencing: advances, challenges and opportunities.</article-title>
          <source>Nat Rev Genet</source>
          <year>2011</year>; <volume>12</volume>:
            <fpage>87</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>98</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21191423</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>ET</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Sandberg</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Luo</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Khrebtukova</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Mayr</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Kingsmore</surname>
              <given-names>SF</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Schroth</surname>
              <given-names>GP</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Burge</surname>
              <given-names>CB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Alternative isoform regulation in human tissue
            transcriptomes.</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>2008</year>;<volume>456</volume>:<fpage>470</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>476</lpage>.
            <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18978772</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jiang</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Wong</surname>
              <given-names>WH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Statistical inferences for isoform expression in RNA-Seq.</article-title>
          <source>Bioinformatics</source>
          <year>2009</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>1026</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1032</lpage>.<pub-id
            pub-id-type="pmid">19244387</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Guttman</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Garber</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Levin</surname>
              <given-names>JZ</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Donaghey</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Robinson</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Adiconis</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Fan</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Koziol</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Gnirke</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Nusbaum</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Rinn</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Lander</surname>
              <given-names>ES</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Regev</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ab initio reconstruction of cell type-specific transcriptomes in mouse
            reveals the conserved multi-exonic structure of lincRNAs.</article-title>
          <source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source>
          <year>2010</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>503</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>510</lpage>.
            <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20436462</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tang</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Barbacioru</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Nordman</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Xu</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Bodeau</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Tuch</surname>
              <given-names>BB</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Siddiqui</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Lao</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Surani</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>mRNA-seq whole-transcriptome analysis of a single cell.</article-title>
          <source>Nat Methods</source>
          <year>2009</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>377</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>382</lpage>.
            <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19349980</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tang</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Barbacioru</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Bao</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Nordman</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Lao</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Surani</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Tracing the derivation of embryonic stem cells from the inner cell mass by
            single-cell RNA-seq analysis.</article-title>
          <source>Cell Stem Cell</source>
          <year>2010</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>468</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>478</lpage>.
            <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20452321</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ramsk&#x000f6;ld</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Luo</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>YC</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Deng</surname>
              <given-names>Q</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Faridani</surname>
              <given-names>OR</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Daniels</surname>
              <given-names>GA</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Khrebtukova</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Loring</surname>
              <given-names>JF</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Laurent</surname>
              <given-names>LC</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Schroth</surname>
              <given-names>GP</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Sandberg</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Full-length mRNA-Seq from single-cell levels of RNA and individual
            circulating tumor cells.</article-title>
          <source>Nat Biotechnol</source>
          <year>2012</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>777</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>782</lpage>.
            <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22820318</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Qiu</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Luo</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Evgrafov</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Schroth</surname>
              <given-names>GP</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Levitt</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Knowles</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Single-neuron RNA-Seq: technical feasibility and
            reproducibility.</article-title>
          <source>Front Genet</source>
          <year>2012</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>124</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid"
            >22934102</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Xue</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Cai</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Cai</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Jiang</surname>
              <given-names>CY</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Feng</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Zeng</surname>
              <given-names>Q</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Cheng</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Sun</surname>
              <given-names>YE</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>JY</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Horvath</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Fan</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genetic programs in human and mouse early embryos revealed by single-cell RNA sequencing.</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>2013</year>;<volume>500</volume>:<fpage>593</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>597</lpage>.
            <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23892778</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tariq</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>HJ</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Jejelowo</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Pourmand</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Whole-transcriptome RNAseq analysis from minute amount of total
            RNA.</article-title>
          <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
          <year>2011</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>e120</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid"
            >21737426</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Adiconis</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Borges-Rivera</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Satija</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>DeLuca</surname>
              <given-names>DS</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Busby</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Berlin</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Sivachenko</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Thompson</surname>
              <given-names>DA</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Wysoker</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Fennell</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Gnirke</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Pochet</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Regev</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Levin</surname>
              <given-names>JZ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Comparative analysis of RNA sequencing methods for degraded or low-input samples.</article-title>
          <source>Nat Methods</source>
          <year>2013</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>623</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>629</lpage>.
            <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23685885</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wu AR, Neff NF, Kalisky T, Dalerba P, Treutlein B,
          Rothenberg ME, Mburu FM, Mantalas GL, Sim S, Clarke MF, Quake SR. Quantitative assessment
          of single-cell RNA-sequencing methods. Nat Methods 2014;11:41&#x02013;46.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bhargava</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Head</surname>
              <given-names>SR</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Ordoukhanian</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Mercola</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>, <name>
              <surname>Subramaniam</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Technical variations in low-input RNA-seq methodologies.</article-title>
          <source>Sci Rep</source>
          <year>2014</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>3678</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid"
            >24419370</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
